Somebody asked me today...
今天有人问我
"Phil, if you could be anywhere, where would you like to be?"
“菲尔，随便让你选个地方，你会想到哪去？”
I said to him, "Probably right here."
我跟他说“大概就是这里”
Elko, Nevada. Our nation's high at 79 today.
内华达州的艾科 今天国内最高气温华氏79度
In California, they'll have warm weather tomorrow...
加州明天会有温暖的天气…
gang wars and some very overpriced real estate.
帮派斗殴和超贵的房地产
Up in the Pacific Northwest, they'll have some very tall trees.
太平洋岸西北部会有很高大的树
It will be clear across the Rockies and the Great Plains.
(卫星图片) 落矶山脉天气晴朗…
But look out, here comes trouble.
不过要小心，有麻烦要来了
Oh, boy! Front coming our way. Look out.
天啊！ 直接对着我们而来，小心
What will that mean to us in the Three Rivers area?
那对三河地区会有什么影响？
One of these big blue things! This cold, frigid, Arctic air.
这一大片蓝色区块 是寒冷的北极气团
This big mass out of the north.
从北方来的大片云团
It will meet up with all this moisture coming out of the Gulf...
它会和来自墨西哥湾 的湿热空气相遇
mix together at high altitudes and cause some snow.
在高海拔地区混合 然后会导致降雪
It won't hit us here in Pittsburgh. It will push off and hit Altoona.
它不会侵袭匹兹堡 而会抵达亚图纳
Close call.
好险
Let's take a look at the five-day.
让我们来看未来五天的天气预测
Nothing to be too scared about.
没什么好担心的
Bundle up warm, but leave your galoshes at home.
穿得暖和一点，可是不必穿雨靴
I won't be here for the 10:00.
十点钟我不会在这里
Tomorrow is Groundhog Day, and I'm going out to Punxsutawney...
明天是土拨鼠节
for our country's oldest groundhog festival.
参加全国历史最久的土拨鼠节庆
According to the legend, tomorrow, February 2...
根据传说，明天2月2日
if the groundhog sees his shadow, we'll have six more weeks of winter.
如果土拨鼠看到自己的影子 冬天就还有6周
- Keep your fingers crossed. - Sounds like a lot of fun.
-祈求好运吧 -好像很好玩的样子
This is your third year in a row isn't it?
这是你连续第3年去吧？
Four, Nan.
第4年
Thanks, Phil.
谢谢你，菲尔
Up next: Diane Kingman looks at sex and violence in the movies.
接下来，黛安金曼 要探讨电影中的性与暴力
Stay with us.
不要走开
- We're clear. - Have fun in Punxsutawney.
-好了 -到普苏塔尼玩得愉快
For your information, Hairdo...
告诉你，美发妹
there is a major network interested in me.
有家无线电视台对我有兴趣
That would be the Home Shopping Network.
一定是购物频道
Thanks, Larry. Go wait in the van.
谢了，赖瑞，到车上等
That was nice. "Big trees."
说得真妙，“高大的树”
Stop, Henny. Can you handle the 10:00 or not?
闭嘴，亨利 你能不能报十点的气象？
If you don't want to rush back, I can do the 5:00 tomorrow.
如果你不想太赶的话 我可以报明天5点那节
I want to stay an extra second in Punxsutawney? Please!
我会在普苏塔尼多待一秒钟？ 别闹了！
Rita thinks it would be great to stay for some of the other events...
丽塔觉得留在那边 参加别的活动很不错
get some incredible footage.
可以拍一些很棒的镜头
The people and the fun, the excitement.
群众、欢乐还有刺激
You haven't worked with her yet. She's really nice.
你还没跟她共事过，她人很好
She's gonna be a really good producer.
她是很好的制作人
You guys will have fun.
你们会很开心的
She's fun, but not my kind of fun. I will be here for the 5:00. Rita.
她的开心和我的不一样 我5点会来，丽塔
Can you keep a secret, Larry?
可以帮我保密吗，赖瑞？
I'm probably leaving PBH.
我可能会离开PBH
So this will be the last time we do the Groundhog together.
这是我们最后一次 一起报导土拨鼠节
What's wrong with the Groundhog Festival?
土拨鼠节有什么不好？
In San Diego, I covered the swallows returning to Capistrano six years.
我在圣地牙哥报导 燕子返回卡皮卓诺6年
Someday somebody will see me interviewing a groundhog...
总有一天会有人看到 我在访问土拨鼠
and think I don't have a future.
我根本没有前途
I think it's a nice story.
那会是很好的报导
He comes out, and he looks around.
它爬出来，四处看看
He wrinkles up his little nose. He sees his shadow or he doesn't see it.
皱起小鼻子 到底有没有看到影子呢
It's nice. People like it.
很棒，观众会喜欢
You are new, aren't you?
你是新来的吧？
People like blood sausage too.
观众也喜欢血香肠
People are morons.
观众是白痴
Nice attitude.
你的态度还真不错
Look in the mirror and see what you look like doing that groundhog thing.
照照镜子，看你报导土拨鼠节 是什么德性
For me? Once?
做一次给我看
He comes out and looks at his little shadow.
它爬出来，看到自己的影子
- Would you like some blood sausage? - I like blood sausage.
-要来点血香肠吗？ -我喜欢血香肠
Rita, I can't stay here.
丽塔，我不能住在这里
- Prima donna. - I'll handle it. What's the matter?
-真难搞 -我来处理，怎么回事？
I hate this place. I stayed here two years ago. I was miserable.
我讨厌这地方 我2年前就来过，当时好惨
- It's a fleabag. I'm not staying here. - You're not staying here.
-这根本是狗窝，我不要住在这里 -你不用住在这里
I'm not?
-不用吗？ -对啊
Larry's dropping me off. I booked you in a nice bed-and-breakfast.
赖瑞只是让我下车 我帮你订了很棒的旅馆
Great. I think this is the trait of a really good producer:
很好 这是优秀制作人必备的特点
Keep the talent happy.
让明星开心
Anything I can do.
我很乐意效劳
Would you help me with my pelvic tilt?
愿意服侍我上厕所吗？
Within reason.
别得寸进尺
Would you like to have dinner with Larry and me?
你要和我跟赖瑞吃晚餐吗？
No, thank you. I've seen Larry eat.
不，谢谢 我看过赖瑞吃饭的德性
Get your sleep. I'll see you in the morning.
去睡觉吧，明天早上见
Don't be late.
别迟到
Did he actually call himself"the talent"?
他真的自称为“明星”吗？
Okay, campers, rise and shine.
该起床了
Don't forget your booties because it's cold out there today.
别忘了你的装备 今天外面很冷
It's cold out there every day. What is this, Miami Beach?
外面每天都很冷 难道这里是迈阿密海滩吗？
Not hardly. You can expect hazardous travel later with that blizzard thing.
不可能，等一下你就 可以在大风雪中冒险了
"That blizzard thing"? Here's the report.
“大风雪”？接下来是气象报告
The National Weather Service is calling for a big blizzard thing.
气象局说会有大风雪
They are. But there's another reason why today is especially exciting.
对，不过今天特别刺激 还有一个原因
Especially cold.
天气特别冷
The big question on everybody's lips...
每个人唇边 都冒出一个大问题
On their chapped lips.
龟裂的嘴唇
Do you think Phil will come out and see his shadow?
你想菲尔出来会看到影子吗？
- Punxsutawney Phil. - That's right, woodchuck chuckers.
-普苏塔尼菲尔 -没错，土拨鼠投手
It's Groundhog Day!
今天是土拨鼠节！
- Get up and check that hog! - Come here, groundhog!
-起来看土拨鼠吧！ -过来，土拨鼠
Good morning.
早安
- You off to see the groundhog? - I am.
-你会去看土拨鼠吗？ -会
Do you think it will be an early spring?
今年会是早春吗？
I'm predicting March 21.
我预测是3月21日
Good guess.
猜得好
I think that actually is the first day of spring.
我想那会是春天的第一天
Did you sleep well, Mr. Connors?
睡得好吗，康纳先生？
I slept alone, Mrs. Lancaster.
我一个人睡，蓝太太
- Would you like some coffee? - Is there any possibility...
-想喝咖啡吗？ -今天早上
of getting an espresso or a cappuccino this morning?
有没有浓缩咖啡或卡布奇诺？
I really don't know.
我真的不知道…
How to spell "espresso" or "cappuccino."
“浓缩咖啡”或“卡布奇诺” 怎么拼？
This looks fine.
这就可以了
- I hope you enjoy the festivities. - I'm sure I will.
-祝你这次玩得愉快 -一定会的
There's talk of a blizzard.
听说有大风雪
We may catch a break and have that blizzard blow by us.
天气会有变化 大风雪会被吹走
All this moisture coming up out of the south...
这股从南方来的湿热空气
will probably push on east of us.
可能会吹到我们的东边
At high altitudes it will crystallize and give us what we call snow.
它会在高海拔地区结晶 为我们带来降雪
Probably will be some accumulation...
可能会有积雪
but here in Punxsutawney our high will be about 30 today, teens tonight.
不过今天普苏塔尼最高温会达到 华氏30度，晚上则有十几度
Chance of precipitation about 20 percent today and tomorrow.
今明两天气温骤降的机率 大约20%
Did you want to talk about the weather or were you just making chitchat?
你是想谈天气还是在闲聊？
- Chitchat. - See you later.
-闲聊 -回头见
- Bye. - Will you be checking out today?
-再见 -你今天会退房吗？
Chance of departure today: 100 percent.
今天离开的机率是100%
Phil Connors? I thought that was you!
菲尔康纳？我就知道是你！
How you doing? Thanks for watching.
你好吗？谢谢观赏
Don't tell me you don't remember me. I sure as heck-fire remember you.
别说你不记得我 我可是记得很清楚喔
- Not a chance. - Ned Ryerson!
-想不起来 -尼德莱尔森
Needlenose Ned. Ned the Head.
尖鼻子尼德、秃头尼德
Come on, buddy. Case Western High.
少来了，老兄，西凯高中
I did the whistling belly button trick at the high school talent show. Bing!
我表演过肚脐吹口哨，乒！
Got the shingles real bad senior year, almost didn't graduate.
高三得了严重的带状疱疹 差点毕不了业
Bing again!
乒！
I dated your sister Mary Pat till you told me not to anymore.
我跟你妹玛莉约会过 直到你阻止我为止
Did you turn pro with that belly button thing or what?
你后来跑去表演 职业肚皮秀了吗？
- I sell insurance. - What a shock.
-我在拉保险 -令人震惊
Do you have life insurance? You could always use a little more.
你有保寿险吗？ 随时都能再多买一份喔
Am I right or am I right or am I right? Right?
对不对？对不对？
I would love to stand here and talk with you, but I'm not going to.
我很想站在这里跟你聊 可是我不行
- See you. - I'll walk with you.
-再见 -我陪你走
Whenever I see an opportunity now, I charge it like a bull.
我只要遇到机会 就会像牛一样紧追不放
Ned the Bull, that's me now.
我现在是猛牛尼德
I have friends who live and die by the actuarial tables.
我有朋友靠保险金发财
It's all one big crap shoot.
实在很走运
Have you ever heard of single premium life?
你听过一次缴终身保险吗？
I think that really could be the ticket for you.
非常适合你
God! It is so good to see you!
天啊！见到你真高兴！
- What are you doing for dinner? - Something else.
-你晚餐时间有什么计划？ -我有事
It's been great seeing you, Needlehead. Take care.
见到你真好 尖头，保重
Watch out for that first step. It's a doozy!
小心那一步，很重要！
Strike up the music The band has begun
奏起音乐，乐队刚开始演奏
The Pennsylvania Polka
宾州波尔卡舞曲
Pick out your partner and join in the fun
邀请你的伙伴一起来玩
It started in Scranton It's now number one
它起源自史坎顿 现在已是第一名
It's gonna entertain you
会让人开心无比
Where have you been?
你到哪去了？
It was horrible. A giant leech got me.
好可怕，我被一条大水蛭缠上
You're missing all the fun. These people are great.
你错过了很好玩的东西 这些人太棒了
Some have been partying all night. They sing until they get too cold...
有人彻夜狂欢 一直唱到冷得受不了
then they sit by the fire, get warm and sing some more.
然后就坐在火堆旁取暖 又继续唱歌
They're hicks, Rita.
他们是乡下人，丽塔
Did you sleep okay without me? You tossed and turned, didn't you?
没有我你睡得还好吗？ 是不是辗转难眠？
- You're incredible. - Who told you?
-你太离谱了(厉害) -谁说的？
It's groundhog time.
土拨鼠时间到了
On me in three.
倒数，3…
Two, one.
2、1
Once a year, the eyes of the nation turn to this tiny Pennsylvania hamlet...
每年此时，全国的焦点
to watch a master at work.
想看一名大师工作的情形
The master? Punxsutawney Phil...
这位大师就是普苏塔尼的菲尔
the world's most famous weatherman, the groundhog...
全球最著名的气象预报员
who, as legend has it, can predict the coming of an early spring.
传说它能预言早春的降临
The question we have to ask ourselves today is, "Does Phil feel lucky?"
今天我们要自问的问题是
Then it's the same old schtick.
(菲尔) 然后又是同样的老把戏
The guy with the big stick raps on the door.
拿着大棍子的家伙敲门
They pull the little rat out. They talk to him.
把那只老鼠抱出来 跟它说话
The rat talks back and then they tell us what's gonna happen.
老鼠回答他 然后他们就说会发生什么事
Isn't he cute?
它很可爱吧？
You like your guys with prominent upper teeth?
你喜欢男友有暴牙吗？
"This February 2, at 7:20 and 30 seconds...
今年2月2日 7点20分30秒
Punxsutawney Phil, the seer of seers...
普苏塔尼的菲尔，先知中的先知
prognosticator of prognosticators...
预言家中的预言家
emerged reluctantly, but alertly...
很不情愿地出现在
in Punxsutawney, Pennsylvania...
宾州的普苏塔尼
and stated in Groundhogese...
它用土拨鼠语说
'I definitely see a shadow."'
“我看到了影子”
Sorry, folks. Six more weeks of winter.
抱歉，各位 冬天还有6周
On me in three. Two, one.
倒数3、2、1
Television really fails to capture the true excitement...
电视没办法捕捉到 一只大松鼠…
of a large squirrel predicting the weather.
预测天气的真实兴奋感
I, for one, am very grateful to have been here.
我很感激能到这里来
From Punxsutawney, this is Phil Connors. So long.
菲尔康纳在普苏塔尼的报导，再会
Want to try it again without the sarcasm?
想用不嘲讽的方式 再试一次吗？
We got it. I'm out of here.
拍完了，我要走了
Prima donnas.
真难搞
Boy, take a look at this.
你们看看
- What is going on? - I don't know.
-怎么回事？ -我不知道
Perhaps it's that giant blizzard we're not supposed to get.
也许是我们不该遇到的大风雪
This is impossible.
不可能
Nobody honks this horn but me, pal.
只有我才能按喇叭
Take this rig out of here.
把车子拖走
Commander, what's going on?
警官，怎么回事？
There's nothing going on. We're closing the road.
没事，要封闭路面
- Big blizzard moving in. - What blizzard? It's a couple flakes.
-大风雪逼近了 -什么风雪？只是雪花而已
Don't you listen to the weather? We got a major storm here.
你没听气象预报吗？ 这里有大风暴
I make the weather!
我是报气象的！
All this moisture coming up out of the Gulf...
从墨西哥湾来的湿热空气
will push off to the east and hit Altoona.
会往东移，侵袭亚图纳
Pal, you got that moisture on your head.
老兄，你头上有雪
You can go back to Punxsutawney or you can freeze to death.
不回普苏塔尼就会冻死在这里
It's your choice. What's it gonna be?
看你的选择，怎么样？
I'm thinking.
我在想
All the long-distance lines are down?
所有长途线路都不通？
What about the satellite? Is it snowing in space?
卫星呢？太空中也下雪吗？
Don't you have a line you keep open for emergencies or for celebrities?
难道没有线路开放 供紧急状况或名人使用吗？
I'm both. I'm a celebrity in an emergency.
我两者都是 我是发生紧急状况的名人
Can you patch me through on that line, please?
帮我接通好吗？
Can I have one more with booze in it?
可以再来杯酒吗？
I like it here.
我好喜欢这里
Phil, are you going to the groundhog dinner?
菲尔，你会参加土拨鼠晚餐吗？
I had groundhog for lunch. It wasn't bad.
我午餐吃了土拨鼠 味道还不错
Tastes like chicken. You two run along.
满像鸡肉的，你们去吧
Looking foxy tonight, man.
今晚很帅喔
Is your troop selling cookies again this year?
你的童子军今年会再卖饼干吗？
That's so funny, Phil.
真好笑，菲尔
What are you gonna do?
你要做什么？
I'm going back to my room and take a hot shower.
回房间洗个热水澡
Maybe read Hustler or something.
说不定看看好色客杂志
Suit yourself.
随便你
God!
天啊
Yo, Mom. Isn't there any hot water?
老妈，没有热水吗？
There wouldn't be today.
今天没有
Of course not. Silly me.
当然没有，我真笨
Sweet dreams.
祝你好梦
Nice going, boys. You're playing yesterday's tape.
干得好，小子 你们播的是昨天的带子
Chapped lips.
龟裂的嘴唇
What the hell?
怎么搞的？
Good morning. Off to see the groundhog?
早安，要去看土拨鼠吗？
Think it will be an early spring?
今年会是早春吗？
Didn't we do this yesterday?
我们昨天谈过了吧？
I don't know what you mean.
我听不懂你的意思
Don't mess with me, Pork Chop.
别耍我，肥猪
- What day is this? - It's February 2. Groundhog Day.
-今天几号？ -2月2日土拨鼠节
I thought it was yesterday.
我以为是昨天
Did you sleep well, Mr. Connors?
睡得好吗，康纳先生？
Did I sleep well?
睡得好吗？
- Would you like some coffee? - Please. I think I'll have a double.
-想喝点咖啡吗？ -好，我要双份的
I hope you enjoy the festivities.
祝你玩得开心
There's talk of a blizzard.
听说有大风雪
Do you ever have deja vu?
你有 “似曾相识”(法语)的感觉吗？
I don't think so, but I could check with the kitchen.
应该没有，但我可以问厨房
That's okay. Thank you.
没关系，谢谢
Will you be checking out today?
你今天要退房吗？
I'd say the chance of departure is 80 percent.
我离开的机率是80%
Seventy-five, eighty.
75，80
Excuse me.
对不起
Where is everybody going?
大家要去哪？
To Gobbler's Knob. It's Groundhog Day.
去火鸡丘，今天是土拨鼠节
It's still just once a year, isn't it?
那还是一年一次吧？
Phil Connors. I thought that was you.
菲尔康纳，我就知道是你
Don't you say you don't remember me. I sure as heck-fire remember you.
别说你不记得我 我可是记得很清楚喔
Ned Ryerson?
尼德莱尔森？
Bing! First shot right out of the box!
乒！一猜就中！
How's it going, old buddy?
你好吗，老兄？
Actually, I'm not feeling well. Would you excuse me?
我不太舒服，失陪了
It's funny you should mention your health.
真好玩，你竟然提到你的健康
You will never guess what I do now.
你绝对猜不到我做哪一行
- Do you sell insurance? - Bing again!
-拉保险吗？ -又猜中了
You are sharp as a tack today.
你今天真是聪明
Do you have life insurance? If you do, you could always use more.
你有寿险吗？如果有 还可以多买一点
Right? Who couldn't?
对吧？谁不是呢？
You know something? I got a feeling you ain't got any.
我感觉得到你没有保险
- Am I right or am I right? - I gotta go.
-对不对？ -我要走了
Watch out for that first step. It's a doozy.
小心那一步，很重要
- Where have you been? - Rita, do me a favor.
-你到哪去了？ -丽塔，帮我一个忙
I need someone to give me a good hard slap in the face.
我需要有人好好赏我一巴掌
- How's that? - Good.
-怎么样？ -很好
If you need help with the other cheek, let me know. I'm right here.
右脸也需要的话通知我 随时奉陪
- Something's going on. - Are you drunk or something?
-不太对劲 -你是醉了还是怎样？
Drunk's more fun. Can I be serious for a minute?
喝醉有趣多了 我能严肃一分钟吗？
- I don't know. Can you? - I'm being serious.
-我不知道，你能吗？ -我现在很严肃
I'm having a problem. I may be having a problem.
我有问题了，可能有问题了
- It's groundhog time. - I knew you would say that.
-土拨鼠时间到了 -我就知道你会那么说
I really feel weird.
我真的觉得很奇怪
Let's just do this, then we'll talk.
我们先拍完再谈
On me in three.
倒数3…
Two, one.
2、1
It's Groundhog Day again.
土拨鼠节又到了
That must mean we're at Gobbler's Knob waiting for the forecast...
我们一定会在火鸡丘等待
from the world's most famous groundhog weatherman...
全球最著名的土拨鼠预报员
Punxsutawney Phil...
普苏塔尼菲尔
who's just about to tell us how much more winter we can expect.
它将告诉我们冬天还有多久
This is a riot.
好热闹哦
Isn't he cute?
它很可爱吧？
Yeah, Sport, I know there's a blizzard.
对，老兄，我知道有大风雪
When are the long-distance lines gonna be repaired?
长途线路什么时候修好？
What if there is no tomorrow? There wasn't one today.
万一没有明天呢？ 今天就没有啊
Hello?
喂？
Good morning. Off to see the groundhog?
早安，要去看土拨鼠吗？
Did you sleep well, Mr...
睡得好吗，康…
I thought...
我就知道…
Don't say you don't remember me. I sure as heck-fire remember you.
别说你不记得我 我可是记得很清楚喔
It's me, Ned Ryerson!
是我，尼德莱尔森！
Needlenose Ned. Ned the Head. Come on, buddy. Case Western...
尖鼻子尼德，秃头尼德 老兄，西凯…
- Where have you been? - Can we talk about a nonwork matter?
-你到哪去了？ -谈点工作以外的事好吗？
- You never talk about work. - We really have to talk. Come on.
-你从来不谈工作 -我们真的需要谈谈，来
- It's a creative meeting. Forget it. - Wait a second. We've got work to do.
-这是创意会议，别想跟来 -等等，我们有工作要做
I don't. I've already done it twice.
我没有，我已经做2次了
When you get finished, meet me in the diner.
等你拍完，跟我在餐厅碰面
- What's that all about? - I don't know.
-怎么回事？ -不知道
Prima donnas.
真难搞
More coffee, hon?
还要咖啡吗？
No, thanks. Just the check, please.
不，谢了，买单
- These sticky buns are heaven. - Aren't they?
-甜点真可口 -那当然
Just put that anywhere, pal.
随便放
Good save.
救得好
Tell me why you're too sick to work, and it better be good.
你怎会病到不能工作 理由最好漂亮一点
I'm reliving the same day over and over.
我不断重覆经历同一天
Groundhog Day. Today.
土拨鼠节，今天
I'm waiting for the punch line.
我在等你的笑点
Really. This is the third time.
真的，这是第三次了
It's like yesterday never happened.
就像昨天根本没发生过
I am racking my brain, but I can't imagine why you'd make this up.
我一直搞不懂 你干嘛编这套故事
I'm not making it up. I am asking you for help!
我没有编，我在求你帮忙
What do you want me to do?
你要我怎么做？
I don't know! You're a producer, come up with something.
我不知道，你是制作人 想想办法
You want my advice?
想听我的建议吗？
You should get your head examined if you expect me to believe that story.
要我相信你的说法的话 最好去检查你的脑袋，菲尔
Like the groundhog Phil?
你和土拨鼠菲尔同名？
Look out for your shadow, pal.
找找你的影子，老兄
Morons, your bus is leaving.
白痴，你的公车要走了
You guys ready? We better get going...
好了吗？天气变坏前 最好赶快离开
I'm not going back to Pittsburgh.
我不要回匹兹堡
- Why not? - Because of the blizzard.
-为什么？ -因为有大风雪
You said that would hit Altoona.
你说它会侵袭亚图纳
I know that's what I said.
我知道我是那么说
I think you need help.
我想你需要帮忙
That's what I've been saying. I need help.
我也一直说我需要帮忙
No spots, no clots...
没有斑点、血块
no tumors, no lesions...
没有肿瘤、机能障碍
no aneurisms.
没有动脉瘤
None that I can see.
我看没什么问题
If you want a CAT scan or an MRI, you have to go into Pittsburgh.
想做断层扫瞄或磁共振成像 就得回匹兹堡
I can't go into Pittsburgh.
我没办法回匹兹堡
- Why can't you go into Pittsburgh? - There's a blizzard.
-为什么？ -有大风雪
Right. The blizzard.
对，大风雪
You know what you may need, Mr. Connors?
知道你需要什么吗，康纳先生？
A biopsy.
切片检查
A psychiatrist.
精神科医生
That's an unusual problem, Mr. Connors.
这是个很不寻常的问题
Most of my work is with couples, families.
我的病人大多是夫妻、一家人
I have an alcoholic now.
现在有一个酒鬼
You went to college, right? It wasn't veterinary psychology, was it?
你上过大学吧？ 该不会是念兽医心理学吧？
Didn't you take some course that covered this stuff?
你有没有修过跟这有关的课？
Sort of. I guess.
应该算有吧
Abnormal psychology.
变态心理学
So, what do I do?
我该怎么办？
I think we should meet again.
你应该再来
How's tomorrow for you?
明天可以吗？
Is that not good?
不好吗？
I was in the Virgin Islands once.
我有一次去维京群岛
I met a girl.
遇到一个女孩子
We ate lobster, drank pina coladas.
我们一起吃龙虾、喝鸡尾酒
At sunset, we made love like sea otters.
黄昏时我们像海獭一样做爱
That was a pretty good day.
那真是美好的一天
Why couldn't I get that day over and over and over?
我为何不能反覆过那一天？
You know, some guys would look at this glass...
有些人看到这个玻璃杯子
and they would say, "That glass is half empty."
他们会说“这杯子半空”
Other guys would say, "That glass is half full."
其他人会说“这杯子半满”
I peg you as a "glass is half empty" kind of guy. Am I right?
我认为你是“半空”型的人 对不对？
What would you do if you were stuck in one place...
如果你困在一个地方 每天都完全一样
and every day was exactly the same, and nothing that you did mattered?
做什么都改变不了状况 你会怎么办？
That sums it up for me.
我的人生就是那样
Good luck. I'll drop you off.
祝你好运，我半路让你下车
- This thing sticks. You gotta jiggle it. - Come on up here.
-卡住了，要摇一下 -起来
- My gosh. - Give me your keys, pal.
-天啊 -钥匙给我
Friends don't let friends drive. Stand up here. Take a deep breath.
是朋友就不会让你开车 站好，深呼吸
You feel okay? Really?
你还好吗？真的？
You're all right.
你没事了
You want to throw up here or in the car?
想在这里还是车上吐？
- I think both. - Come on.
-都要 -来吧
I don't think I should be driving.
我不该开车
I don't either. Watch your head.
我想也是，小心头
Watch your knees. Don't break anything.
小心膝盖，别受伤了
All right. Let's not forget seat belts.
好，别忘了系安全带
Who else could go for some flapjacks right now?
还有谁能去买煎饼？
Let me ask you guys a question.
我问你们一个问题
- Shoot. - What if there were no tomorrow?
-说吧 -万一没有明天呢？
No tomorrow? That would mean there would be no consequences.
没有明天？也就是没有结果
There would be no hangovers. We could do whatever we wanted!
不会有宿醉 我们可以随心所欲！
That's true. We could do whatever we want.
没错，想做什么就做什么
If we wanted to hit mailboxes, we could let Ralph drive!
要是想撞烂邮筒，就让雷夫开车了
- I think they want you to stop. - Hang on.
-我想他们要你停车 -抓好
It's the same thing your whole life:
人生就是这么一回事
"Clean up your room." " Stand up straight." " Pick up your feet."
“清理房间”、“站好” “脚抬起来”
"Take it like a man." "Be nice to your sister."
“像个男人有担当” “对你妹好一点”
"Don't mix beer and wine, ever."
“别把啤酒和葡萄酒混合”
"Don't drive on the railroad tracks."
“别在铁轨上开车”
Phil, that's one I happen to agree with.
菲尔，这点我刚好同意
I don't know, Gus.
我不知道，贾斯
Sometimes I think you just have to take the big chances.
我想有时候就该孤注一掷
This is the police! Pull over immediately!
我们是警察！立刻停车
We're talking in here.
我们在说话
I'm betting he'll swerve first.
我猜他会先转弯
I'm not gonna live by their rules anymore.
我不要再照别人的规则生活了
- I noticed that. - You make choices and live with them.
-我注意到了 -做了选择就要接受
My knee.
我的膝盖
Let me handle this.
让我来应付
Three cheeseburgers, two large fries...
三个吉士汉堡，两份大薯条
two chocolate shakes and one large Coke.
两杯巧克力奶昔 还有一杯大可乐
- And some flapjacks. - Too early for flapjacks?
-还有煎饼 -吃煎饼太早了吗？
Rise and shine, campers!
快起床！
Don't forget your booties because it's cold out there today!
别忘了装备，今天外面很冷
It's cold out there every day. What is this, Miami Beach? Not hardly.
外面每天都很冷 这里是迈阿密海滩吗？不可能
Slept like a baby. Thank you.
睡得像婴儿一样，谢谢
- I'd love some of your coffee. - I hope...
-我想来点咖啡 -你想…
Flurries moving in later, but the blizzard will hit outside of town.
晚一点会下雪 不过大风雪会侵袭城外
Mrs. Lancaster, was anybody looking for me here this morning?
蓝太太，今天早上有人找我吗？
Perhaps a state official? Maybe a blue hat, gun, nightstick?
也许是戴蓝帽、佩枪 有警棍的州警？
No one like that. Will there be?
没有那种人，会有吗？
Apparently not.
显然没有
Hold my room for me, please. I'm staying an extra day.
请帮我保留房间 我要多待一天
Catch you tomorrow, Pops.
明天见，老爹
I like to see a man of advancing years throwing caution to the wind.
我喜欢看中年人做事不顾后果
It's inspiring, in a way.
满激励人心的
My years are not advancing as fast as you might think.
我的年纪没你想的那么老
More coffee, hon?
还要咖啡吗？
Just keep it coming, please.
拿过来
Sure thing.
好
Just put that anywhere, pal.
随便放
Good save.
救得好
Don't you worry about cholesterol, lung cancer, love handles?
你不担心胆固醇、肺癌吗？
I don't worry about anything anymore.
我什么都不担心了
What makes you so special? Everybody worries about something.
你怎么会这么特别？ 大家总有事会担心
That's exactly what makes me so special. I don't even have to floss.
所以我才特别 我甚至不用牙线剔牙
What?
怎样？
"The wretch, concentered all in self...
“可怜的人只会注意自己”
Living, shall forfeit fair renown...
“生活，会丧失名声”
And, doubly dying, shall go down...
“而双重的死亡 将从他出现的地方”
To the vile dust, from whence he sprung...
“坠落到污秽的尘埃中”
Unwept, unhonor'd, and unsung."
“无人哀悼、尊崇、歌颂”
Sir Walter Scott.
华特史考特爵士写的
- You don't like poetry? - I love poetry.
-你不喜欢诗？ -我很爱诗
I just thought that was Willard Scott. I was confused.
我以为是威勒史考特 我都搞糊涂了
Do you think I'm acting like this because I'm egocentric?
你想我会这样 是因为太自我中心吗？
I know you're egocentric. It's your defining characteristic.
我知道你很自我中心 那是你的特点
Are you guys ready? We better get going to stay ahead of the weather.
你们好了没？ 趁天气没变坏前赶快出发
Thanks, Larry. Would you like a doggie bag?
谢了，赖瑞 需要打包吗？
- I'll stay here and finish. - I thought you hated this town.
-我留在这里吃完 -我以为你不喜欢这里
It's beginning to grow on me.
我越来越喜欢了
Larry, quit staring.
赖瑞，别看了
These are excellent.
这个很好吃
Did you see the groundhog this morning?
今天早上有看到土拨鼠吗？
I never miss it.
我从不错过
What's your name?
你贵姓大名？
Nancy Taylor. And you are?
南茜泰勒，你是？
- What high school did you go to? - What?
-你上哪所高中？ -什么？
- High school. - Lincoln, in Pittsburgh.
-高中 -林肯高中，在匹兹堡
- Who are you? - Who was your senior English teacher?
-你是谁？ -你高三的英文老师是谁？
Are you kidding?
你在开玩笑吗？
- Your 12th-grade English teacher was... - Mrs. Walsh.
-你高三的英文老师是… -华许老师
Nancy. Lincoln. Walsh. Thanks very much.
南茜，林肯，华许 谢谢
Lincoln High School.
林肯高中
I sat next to you in Mrs. Walsh's English class.
华许老师的课我坐你隔壁
I'm sorry.
对不起…
- That's amazing. - You don't remember me, do you?
-好巧 -你不记得我了吧？
I even asked you to the prom.
我还邀请你参加毕业舞会
I was short, and I've sprouted.
当时我很矮，后来长高了
Gosh! How are you?
天啊，你好吗？
Great. You look terrific.
很好，你看起来美极了
You look very terrific.
简直美呆了
- I have to do this report. - Are you a reporter?
-我得做这项报导 -你是记者？
I'm a weatherman with Channel 9 Pittsburgh.
我是匹兹堡第9频道的 气象播报员
I should have known. That's great!
我早该知道，太好了！
Maybe later we could...
或许晚一点我们可以…
Whatever.
什么都好
Stay right here. Promise me?
待在这里，答应我？
I'll be right back. Wish me luck.
我马上回来，祝我好运
Good luck!
祝你好运！
Who's Rita?
谁是丽塔？
How should I know?
我怎么知道？
Is this some kind of one-night stand?
这算什么？一夜情吗？
On the contrary, Nancy. I love you.
刚好相反，南茜 我爱你
I've always loved you.
我一直爱着你
This is gonna seem sudden, but...
这么说会很突兀，但是…
Nancy, will you be my wife?
南茜，你愿意当我的老婆吗？
Whatever.
随便
A gust of wind.
一阵强风吹
A dog barks.
狗开始叫
Cue the truck.
卡车进来
Exit Herman.
赫曼走出来
Walk into the bank.
(北方联邦储蓄银行) 走进银行
Exit Felix. Stand there with a not-so-bright look on your face.
菲力走出来，脸色不太好看
All right, Doris, come on.
桃莉出场
Fix your bra, honey. That's better.
调整一下胸罩，甜心 这样好多了
"Felix." "How you doing, Doris?"
“菲力” “你好吗，桃莉？”
"Can I have a roll of quarters?"
“换一卷2毛5硬币好吗？”
Ten, nine, eight...
10、9、8
Car. Six, five...
车子、6、5
Quarters.
硬币
- What? - Did I bring out two bags or one?
-怎样？ -我拿2袋还是1袋出来？
I don't know.
不知道
I thought we were going to a costume party.
我以为要参加扮装派对
It's like I said, I love this film.
就像我说的，我爱这部电影
I've seen it over a hundred times.
我看过一百多遍了
I told you to call me Bronco.
叫我布朗柯
Sorry, Bronco.
对不起，布朗柯
My old fiance. They never remember me.
我以前的未婚妻 她们总是不记得我
- That will be one adult and... - Two adults.
-一张全票和… -两张全票
The question we have to ask ourselves today is, "Does Phil feel lucky?"
今天我们要自问的问题是 “菲尔觉得运气如何？”
Rita, if you only had one day to live, what would you do with it?
丽塔，如果你的生命只剩一天 你会怎么过？
I don't know, Phil. What are you dying of?
我不知道，菲尔 你要死了吗？
I mean, the whole world is about to explode. What do you do?
不…假如地球快爆炸了 你怎么办？
I want to know where to put the camera.
我只想知道摄影机要放哪
Are you looking for a date for the weekend?
你在找周末的约会对象吗？
I'm just interested in you.
我对你有兴趣
What do you want? What do you like? What do you think about?
你要什么？你喜欢什么？ 你在想什么？
What kind of men are you interested in?
你对哪种男人有兴趣？
What do you do for fun?
你做什么消遣？
Is this for real or are you trying to make me look like a fool?
你是说真的，还是想捉弄我？
I'm just trying to talk like normal people talk. Isn't this how they talk?
我只想像一般人那样说话 他们不是这样说话的吗？
- Close. - So talk to me.
-差不多 -那就跟我说话
Let me buy you a cup of coffee.
我请你喝杯咖啡
- And a donut. - All right.
-加上一个甜甜圈 -好
What do you want out of life?
你想从生活中得到什么？
I guess I want what everybody wants:
我要每个人都想要的
Career, love, marriage, children.
事业、爱情、婚姻、孩子
Are you seeing anyone?
你现在有对象吗？
I think this is getting too personal.
这问题太隐私了
I don't think I'm ready to share this with you.
我还不准备跟你分享这些
How about you? What do you want?
你呢？你要什么？
What I really want is someone like you.
我想要的是你这样的人
- Please. - Why not?
-拜 -有什么不可以？
What are you looking for? Who is your perfect guy?
你在追寻什么？ 你的理想对象要怎样？
First of all, he's too humble to know he's perfect.
首先，他会很谦虚 明白自己不够完美
That's me.
我就是这样
He's intelligent, supportive, funny.
聪明、支持我、幽默
Me, me, me.
我、我、我
- He's romantic and courageous. - Me also.
-浪漫而且勇敢 -我也是
He's got a good body, but doesn't look in the mirror every two minutes.
他身材很好 但不会没事猛照镜子
I have a great body, and sometimes I go months without looking.
我身材很棒 有时几个月都不照镜子
He's kind, sensitive and gentle.
他善良、体贴又温柔
He's not afraid to cry in front of me.
不怕在我面前哭
This is a man, right?
他是个男人吧？
He likes animals and children, and he'll change poopy diapers.
他喜欢动物和小孩 还会换有大便的尿布
Does he have to use the word "poopy"?
一定要用“大便”这字眼吗？
And he plays an instrument, and he loves his mother.
他会弹奏乐器，爱他的母亲
I am really close on this one.
我真的和这个人很相近
It's Phil Connors.
他是菲尔康纳
Hello. Thanks for watching.
谢谢观赏
So, what are the chances of getting out today?
今天离开的机率有多大？
The van still won't start. Larry's working on it.
车子还是发不动 赖瑞正在想办法
Wouldn't you know it. Can I buy you a drink?
谁知道会怎样 请你喝杯酒好吗？
Jim Beam, ice, water.
金宾威士忌，加冰块，加水
For you, miss?
你呢，小姐？
Sweet vermouth on the rocks with a twist, please.
甜苦艾酒加冰块，放柠檬片
What are the chances of getting out of town today?
今天出城的机率有多大？
The van still won't start. Larry's working on it.
车子还是发不动 赖瑞正在想办法
Wouldn't you know it. Can I buy you a drink?
谁知道会怎样 请你喝杯酒好吗？
Sweet vermouth, rocks with a twist, please.
甜苦艾酒加冰块，放柠檬片
- For you, miss? - The same.
-你呢，小姐？ -一样
- That's my favorite drink. - Mine too.
-那是我最爱喝的酒 -我也是
It always makes me think of Rome, the way the sun hits the buildings.
它总会让我想到罗马 阳光洒在建筑物上的样子
What shall we drink to?
我们要敬什么？
To the groundhog.
敬土拨鼠
I always drink to world peace.
我都敬世界和平
Can I buy you a drink?
请你喝杯酒好吗？
Sweet vermouth, rocks with a twist, please.
甜苦艾酒加冰块，放柠檬片
For you, miss?
你呢，小姐？
The same. That's my favorite drink.
一样，那是我最爱的酒
Mine too.
我也是
It always makes me think of Rome...
它总会让我想到罗马
the way the sun hits the buildings.
阳光洒在建筑物上的样子
What shall we drink to?
我们要敬什么？
I like to say a prayer and drink to world peace.
我想祈祷世界和平
To world peace.
敬世界和平
Amen.
阿门
- This is wonderful. - Didn't I tell you?
-很好吃 -我不是说过了吗？
How do you know so much about Punxsutawney?
你怎么这么了解普苏塔尼？
I've spent a lot of time here.
我常待在这里
- Small town people are more real. - That's how I feel.
-小镇居民实在多了 -那也是我的感觉
Really? Would you like some white chocolate?
真的？想吃白巧克力吗？
- Don't make me sick. - No white chocolate.
-别让我恶心了 -不吃白巧克力
There is something familiar about this.
这感觉好熟悉
- Do you ever have deja vu? - Didn't you just ask me that?
-你有似曾相识的感觉吗？ -你不是刚问过吗？
People place too much emphasis on their careers.
人们太重视事业了
I wish we could all live in the mountains at high altitude.
我希望人们能住在高山上
That's where I see myself in five years.
我希望五年后能办到
- How about you? - I agree.
-你呢？ -我同意
I like to go with the flow, see where it leads me.
我喜欢顺其自然，看会怎样
It's led you here.
结果现在你变成这样
It's a million miles from where I started in college.
我没有学以致用
You weren't in broadcasting or journalism?
你不是念新闻或传播的吗？
Believe it or not, I studied 19th-century French poetry.
信不信由你 我主修19世纪法国诗
What a waste of time.
真是浪费时间
For someone else that would be an incredible waste of time.
对别人来说那非常浪费时间
It was so bold of you to choose that. It's incredible.
你选择那领域真有勇气 难以置信
You must be a very strong person.
你一定是意志很坚强的人
People place too much emphasis on their careers.
人们太重视事业了
I wish we could all live in the mountains, at high altitudes.
我希望人们能住在高山上
That's where I see myself in five years.
我希望五年后能办到
- How about you? - I agree.
-你呢？ -我同意
I like to go with the flow, see what happens.
我喜欢顺其自然，看会怎样
It's gotten you here.
结果你变成现在这样
It's a million miles from where I started in college.
我没有学以致用
You weren't in broadcasting or journalism?
你不是念新闻或传播的吗？
Believe it or not, I studied 19th-century French poetry.
信不信由你 我主修19世纪法国诗
You speak French.
你会说法语
- I haven't done this since I was a kid. - Me neither.
-我长大后就没玩过这个 -我也一样
- It's fun. - It's good, clean fun.
-很好玩 -干净又好玩
I hope that one day I can do this with my own children.
希望有天能和我的孩子一起玩
Where did you get that?
哪里弄来的？
I went over to the snowman shop.
我到一家雪人商店
An assassin!
刺客！
I'll protect you, Your Majesty.
我会保护你，陛下
I shall die for you! You shall not take her!
我愿为你而死 你们不会得逞的
Find cover, my lady!
寻找掩护，小姐
- Nice arm. - I'm getting some good ones.
-臂力不错 -我来丢一些大的雪球
There's a boy. That's a boy. Good try.
那边有一个，丢得不错
- Got him. - Help me.
-丢中了 -拉我一把
- What? - I'm amazed, and I'm not easily amazed.
-怎样？ -我好惊讶，我不常这样的
- About what? - How you can start a day...
-什么事？ -一天开始时的期望…
with one kind of expectation and end up so completely different.
和最后的结果居然完全不同
Do you like the way this day is turning out?
你喜欢今天的结果吗？
I like it very much.
非常喜欢
It's a perfect day. You couldn't plan a day like this.
今天很完美，这是人计划不出来的
You can. It just takes an awful lot of work.
可以，只是会很花功夫
Come on in. I want to show you something.
进来，给你看样东西
- I don't think I should. - I don't think you should either.
-不太好吧 -我想也是
That's why I'll show you one thing and kick you out. Just one minute.
所以看样东西你就得走 一下子就好
It's just lovely.
好温馨
Would you like to sit and stare at the fake fire?
想坐着看假炉火吗？
It's really a wonderful room.
这房间真棒
It is now.
到现在才棒
I don't know. I don't think we should do this.
我不知道，我们不该这么做
I don't either.
我想也是
On second thought, I think we should.
我考虑之后，我们还是该做
It's the perfect end to a perfect day.
这是完美一天的完美句点
It's a little fast for me.
我觉得太快了
Me too.
我也是
Maybe I should go.
也许我该走了
Where would you go?
你要去哪里？
Why? We've got a perfect fire.
为什么？ 我们有完美的炉火
I've got some French poetry here. Baudelaire.
我这里有一首法国诗 是波德莱尔写的
I will read to you.
我给你听
I've got ice cream on the windowsill.
我的窗台上有冰淇淋
Hold on a minute.
等一下
- Rocky Road? - I love Rocky Road.
-香草脆果巧克力？ -我爱死这个了
I thought so.
我想也是
You have to stay.
你得留下来
I'm tired. We can see each other tomorrow.
我累了，我们明天再见面
Tonight. It's gotta be tonight.
今晚，一定要是今晚
- Really. - Just stay for awhile.
-真的 -待一会儿吧
If you like it, stay for a while longer and awhile longer.
你乐意的话，多待一会儿
- Let's not spoil it. - I don't want to spoil it either.
-别搞砸了 -我也不想
You know I can't stay with you.
你明白我不能留下来陪你
Why not? I love you.
为什么？我爱你
You love me?
你爱我？
- You don't even know me. - I know you.
-你根本还不了解我 -我了解你
I can't believe I fell for this.
我不敢相信自己会信以为真
This whole day has just been one long setup.
这一整天都是陷阱
- It hasn't. - And I hate fudge.
-不是 -我痛恨谎言
No white chocolate. No fudge.
没有白巧克力，没有谎言
What are you doing? Are you making some kind of list?
你在做什么？ 你在列什么单子吗？
Did you call my friends and ask what I like and what I don't like?
你有打电话问我朋友 我喜欢和不喜欢什么吗？
- Is this what love is for you? - This is real. This is love.
-这就是你所谓的爱吗？ -这是真的，这是爱
Stop saying that! You must be crazy.
别说了！你一定是疯了
I could never love someone like you. You only love yourself.
我绝不会爱上你这种人 你只爱你自己
That's not true. I don't even like myself. Give me another chance.
不对，我甚至不喜欢自己 再给我一次机会
That's for making me care about you.
你这个感情骗子！
- I haven't done this since I was a kid. - Me neither.
-我长大后就没再玩过 -我也一样
- It's fun. - Good, clean fun too.
-很好玩 -干净又好玩
That's what's missing in the world today.
今天世界缺乏的就是这个
I can't wait to do this with my own children.
我等不及和自己的孩子一起玩
Golly, I want lots of kids!
天啊，我想要很多孩子！
I want to adopt. I want to have my own.
我要领养孩子，还要自己生
I want foster kids. I got this at Snowman City.
我要收养小孩 我在雪人城找到的
Some kid threw a snowball at us!
有个小孩对我们丢雪球
Come here! Let's have some fun!
过来，我们好好玩玩！
I wish these were my own kids!
真希望他们是我的孩子
Are any of you up for adoption?
你们有人打算被领养吗？
Here's a humdinger over here! Wasn't that great?
这里有个很棒的对象 很好玩吧？
Stop it!
住手
Over here!
在这边
Where have you been? You're missing all the fun.
你到哪去了？ 你错过好玩的东西了
You look terrible.
你的样子好糟糕
What happened? Rough night?
怎么了？睡不好吗？
Okay, campers, rise and shine.
快起床
Don't forget your booties because it's cold out there today.
别忘了装备 今天外面很冷
It's cold out there every day.
外面每天都很冷
This country's largest lake, Chapala, is located near the city...
哪个国家其最大的恰帕拉湖 位于瓜达拉哈拉附近？
- Correct. - "Lakes and Rivers," 400.
-答对了 -湖泊与河流，四百元
Seneca is the largest of these lakes in West-Central New York.
纽约州中西部哪个湖群 其中最大的湖是塞尼加湖？
- What are the Finger Lakes? - Correct.
-手指湖 -答对了
- That's amazing. - "Lakes and Rivers" for 600.
湖泊与河流，六百元
This South American lake drains into the smaller lake in Bolivia.
哪个南美洲的湖流入 波利维亚更小的湖？
- What is Titicaca? - Correct.
-的的喀喀湖 -答对了
- "Lakes and Rivers" for 1,000. - Milky colored...
-湖泊与河流，一千元 -因为源自冰河…
- from glacial clay... - What is the Rhone?
答案是隆河
Jim? The Rhone is good for $ 1,000.
吉姆？ 隆河，你获得一千元
- You are $500 off the lead. - Let's go to "Inventors" for 200.
-离领先还有五百元 -我选发明家，两百元
This is pitiful.
真令人同情
A thousand people freezing their butts off, waiting to worship a rat.
一千个人冻得要命 等着要崇拜一只老鼠
What a hype. Groundhog Day used to mean something in this town.
真是天大的骗局 土拨鼠节以前是别有意义的
They used to pull the hog out and eat it!
他们以前把鼠拖出来吃掉！
You're hypocrites, all of you!
你们全都是伪君子！
You got a problem with what I'm saying?
你对我说的话有意见吗？
Untie your tongue, and you come out here and talk.
嘴巴张开，过来说啊
Am I upsetting you, Princess?
我惹你不高兴吗，王妃？
You want a prediction about the weather, you're asking the wrong Phil.
你们想问天气 却问到错的菲尔
I'll give you a winter prediction.
我帮你们预测
It's gonna be cold...
天气会很冷…
it's gonna be gray...
天色会很阴暗…
and it's gonna last you for the rest of your life.
你们一辈子都会那样
Once again, the eyes of the nation have turned here to this...
每年这时候 全国目光都转移到
tiny village in western Pennsylvania.
这个宾州西部的小镇上
There is no way that this winter...
只要这只土拨鼠 一直看到自己的影子
is ever going to end...
今年冬天…
as long as this groundhog keeps seeing his shadow.
就不会结束
I don't see any other way out.
我没办法了
He has to be stopped.
要有人阻止它
I have to stop him.
我得阻止它
Real good, Phil.
很好，菲尔
He's crazy.
他疯了
I'm worried. I think there's something really wrong with Phil.
我好担心 菲尔真的出了问题
There's a lot of things
菲尔真的很不对劲
I've come to the end of me.
我已经快完蛋了
There's no way out now.
没有出路了
I just want you to remember we had a beautiful day together once.
我要你记得 我们曾共度美好的一天
All right, little fella. Good job.
好了，小家伙，干得好
- He smiled at me. Did you see that? - I believe he did.
-它对我笑，看到没？ -我相信它有
Okay, little fella. There you go.
小家伙，进去吧
Hi, mister. Something I can do you for?
先生，有什么事吗？
What are you doing?
你在干嘛？
Jake, get the word out! Somebody kidnapped Phil!
杰克，快通知大家！ 有人绑架菲尔！
We're going after him!
我们去追他！
Why would anybody steal a groundhog?
怎么会有人要偷土拨鼠？
I can probably think of a couple of reasons. Pervert.
我想到几个可能原因，性变态
- He must have just snapped! - This should be good.
-他一定抓狂了 -这下可精彩了
What is he doing? What can he be thinking?
他在干嘛？他在想什么？
That's not bad for a quadruped.
对四只脚的动物来说算不错了
You gotta check your mirrors, just the side of your eye.
要看照后镜
That's it.
对
They're chasing us! Come on, make it fun!
他们在追我们！开快点！
Don't drive angry.
开车别激动
Hot dog! There's no way out except the way we came in. We got him now!
这里没别的出路，逮到他了！
- What is he doing? - I don't know.
-他在干嘛？ -不知道
If you gotta shoot, aim high. I don't wanna hit the groundhog.
要开枪的话，瞄高一点 别打到土拨鼠
We mustn't keep our public waiting.
不能让观众等太久
It's show time.
好戏上场了
All right, on me, Larry, in three!
好，赖瑞，倒数3秒…
Two, one.
2、1
He might be okay.
他说不定没事
Probably not now.
这下大概出事了
Nuts.
混蛋
Did you sleep well, Mr. Connors?
睡得好吗，康纳先生？
Would you like some toast?
想吃土司吗？
- What's going on? - My God.
-怎么回事？ -天啊
That's him.
是他
He was a really great guy.
他真的是个好人
I really liked him a lot.
我真的很喜欢他
I'm sorry. What was that again?
什么，你说什么？
- I'm a god! - You're a god?
-我是神！ -你是神？
I'm a god. I'm not the God, I don't think.
我是神 不过应该不是上帝
Because you survived a car wreck?
只因为你车祸没死？
You ready to order?
要点餐了吗？
I didn't just survive a wreck. I wasn't just blown up yesterday.
我不光是车祸没死 或只是昨天被炸死
I have been stabbed, shot, poisoned...
我被刺杀、枪杀、毒害…
frozen, hung, electrocuted...
冻死、吊死、电击
- and burned. - Really?
-还被火烧 -真的？
Every morning I wake up fine, not a dent in the fender.
每天早上醒来却毫发无伤
- I am an immortal. - Special today is blueberry waffles.
-我不会死 -今日特餐是蓝莓松饼
Why are you telling me this?
你说这些干嘛？
Because I want you to believe in me.
因为我要你相信我
You're not a god. Believe me. This is 12 years of Catholic school talking.
你不是神，相信我 我上过12年天主教学校
I could come back if you're not ready.
我可以等一下再来帮你点
How do you know I'm not a god?
你怎么知道我不是神？
Please! Because it's not possible!
拜！
- I'll come back. - Doris!
-我等一下再来 -桃莉
This is Doris. Her brother-in-law, Carl, owns this diner.
这是桃莉，她姐夫卡尔是老板
She's worked here since she was 17. She wants to see Paris before she dies.
她从17岁就在这里上班 她希望死前能到巴黎一游
- Boy, would I! - What are you doing?
-天啊，我好想去 -你在干嘛？
- Debbie Kleiser and her fiance, Fred. - Do I know you?
-黛比和她的未婚夫佛瑞 -我认识你们吗？
They're supposed to be married this afternoon, but Debbie is reconsidering.
他们本来今天下午要结婚 但是黛比要重新考虑
- What? - Lovely ring.
-什么？ -好美的戒指
This is Bill who's been a waiter for three years...
这是比尔，他当服务生三年了
since he left Penn State and had to get work.
因为他大学不念了，需要工作
He likes the town, paints toy soldiers, and he's gay.
他喜欢这里，会画玩具兵 还是同性恋
I am.
没错
This is Gus. He hates his life here and wishes he'd stayed in the Navy.
这是贾斯，他讨厌这里的生活 希望能留在海军服役
I could have retired on half pay after 20 years.
20年后我退伍还能领半薪
Is this some kind of trick?
这是什么诡计吗？
Maybe the real God uses tricks. Maybe He's not omnipotent.
也许上帝会耍诡计 也许他不是万能的
He's just been around so long, He knows everything.
他只是在我们身边很久了 所以什么都知道
- Who's that? - This is Tom.
-那是谁？ -这是汤姆
He worked in the coal mine till they closed it down.
他是矿工，一直做到矿坑关闭
- Her? - Alice.
-她呢？ -爱莉丝
She came from Ireland as a baby and lived in Erie most of her life.
婴儿时从爱尔兰过来 一辈子都住在艾里
- He's right. - Nancy.
-他说的对 -南茜
She works in the dress shop and makes chipmunk noises when she gets excited.
她在服装店上班 兴奋时会发出花栗鼠的声音
- It's true. - How do you know these people?
-是真的 -你怎么会认识这些人？
I know everything. In five seconds, a waiter will drop a tray of dishes.
我什么都知道，5秒钟后 有个服务生会打破盘子
- Five, four, three, two, one. - This is nuts.
-5、4、3、2、1 -太疯狂了
That's enough.
够了
- Do you know me too? - I know all about you.
-你也了解我吗？ -我了解你的一切
You like producing, but you're hoping for more than Channel 9 Pittsburgh.
你喜欢制作节目 却不希望光待在第9频道
Everyone knows that.
这大家都知道
You like boats, but not the ocean.
你喜欢船，却不喜欢海
You go to a mountain lake in the summer with your family.
夏天你会跟家人 到山上的一座湖
There's a long, wooden dock and a boathouse...
那里有长长的木船渠 还有一间船库
with boards missing from the roof...
屋顶的木板都不见了
and a place you used to crawl underneath to be alone.
还有一个你会爬下去 独处的地方
You're a sucker for French poetry and rhinestones.
你喜欢法文诗和莱因石
You're very generous.
你很大方
You're kind to strangers and children.
你对陌生人和小孩都很和善
And when you stand in the snow, you look like an angel.
当你站在雪地里 就像个天使一样
How are you doing this?
你怎么办到的？
I wake up every day right here...
我说了 我每天在普苏塔尼醒来
in Punxsutawney, and it's always February 2.
每天都是2月2日
There's nothing I can do about it.
我没办法改变这情况
If you still doubt me...
如果你还怀疑的话
in ten seconds...
10秒钟之后
Larry will come through that door and take you away from me...
赖瑞会进来带你走
but you can't let him.
但你不能让他带你走
Please believe me. You've got to believe me.
请相信我，一定要相信我
You ready? We better get going if we're going to stay ahead of the weather.
好了没？趁天气变坏前赶快走
What's that?
(趁天气变坏前赶快走) 那是什么？
Maybe it really is happening.
也许真的发生了
How else could you know so much?
不然你怎么知道那么多？
There is no way. I'm not that smart.
不可能，我没那么聪明
Maybe I should spend the day with you...
也许今天我该跟你在一起
as an objective witness, just to see what happens.
当客观目击者，看发生什么事
This sounds like a science project.
听起来好像科学实验
Concentrate. You gotta want it.
专心一点，丢进去
It's more in the wrist than the finger. It's just gotta...
重点在手腕，不在手指
Be the hat! Come on! Go!
丢进帽子里，丢！
It would take me a year to get good at this.
我要花一年才能学会
Six months. Four to five hours a day, and you'd be an expert.
6个月，每天4到5小时 你就能变成专家
Is this what you do with eternity?
你这样打发永恒的时间吗？
Now you know.
现在你知道了
That's not the worst part.
这还不是最糟的
What's the worst part?
最糟的是什么？
The worst part is that tomorrow you will have forgotten all about this...
最糟的是明天你会忘掉这一切
and you'll treat me like a jerk again.
又会把我当混蛋
- It's all right. I am a jerk. - You're not.
-没关系，我是混蛋 -你不是
It doesn't make any difference.
没什么差别
I've killed myself so many times, I don't even exist anymore.
我已经自杀很多次了 我早就不存在了
Sometimes I wish I had a thousand lifetimes.
有时我倒希望我有上千辈子
I don't know, Phil. Maybe it's not a curse.
我不知道，菲尔 或许这不是诅咒
It just depends on how you look at it.
端看你如何看待它
Gosh, you're an upbeat lady!
天啊，你真是个乐观的女人
- It's been a really nice day for me. - Me too.
-我觉得今天很愉快 -我也是
Maybe, if it's not too boring, we could do it again sometime.
如果不算太无聊的话 改天我们可以再来一次
I hope so.
希望如此
You're still here.
你还在
I thought you were supposed to disappear or I was or something!
我以为你会消失 或我会消失
Not until 6:00.
要等到6点
You rat!
你这小人！
I never said midnight.
我没说过在午夜
- You knew I was waiting for midnight! - Does this mean you're gonna leave?
-你知道我在等午夜 -你要走了吗？
Good.
好
I'm sorry.
对不起
It's all right. You can fall asleep.
没关系，你可以睡
I promise I won't touch you, much.
我保证不碰你…太多
That's all right. I'm not tired.
没关系，我不累
What were you saying?
你刚刚说什么？
I think the last thing that you heard was...
你听到最后一句话是
"Only God can make a tree."
“只有上帝能造树”
Really?
真的？
What I wanted to say was...
我想说的是
I think you're the kindest, sweetest, prettiest person...
你是我一生中见过 最善良、体贴…
I've ever met in my life.
最美丽的人
I've never seen anyone...
我没见过…
that's nicer to people than you are.
比你待人更好的人
The first time I saw you...
第一次见到你
something happened to me.
我就有种奇妙的感觉
I never told you, but...
我没告诉过你，但…
I knew that I wanted to hold you as hard as I could.
我知道我要紧紧地拥抱你
I don't deserve someone like you.
我配不上你
But if I ever could...
但如果可以
I swear I would love you...
我发誓我会爱你
for the rest of my life.
一生一世
Did you say something?
你刚才说什么？
Good night.
晚安
Who wants coffee? Get it while it's hot.
谁要咖啡？趁热喝
Thanks, Phil.
谢了，菲尔
- Larry? Skim milk, two sugars. - Thanks, Phil.
-赖瑞？脱脂牛奶，2匙糖 -谢了，菲尔
- Pastry? - We're just setting up.
-点心？ -我们在架机器
Take your pick.
自己挑
Thanks. Raspberry. Great.
谢谢，覆盆子，好棒
I was just talking with Buster Green, the head groundhog honcho.
我刚跟巴斯特谈过 他是活动主办人
He said if we set up over here, we might get a better shot.
他说机器架在那边 会拍到比较好的镜头
- What do you think? - Sounds good.
-你觉得如何？ -好像不错
What do you think?
你觉得呢？
Let's go for it.
我们过去吧
- Good work. - Maybe we'll get lucky.
-干得好 -我们运气好
Let me help you with the heavy stuff.
我帮你搬器材
You got your coffee. I'll get it.
你喝你的咖啡，我来
We never talk. Do you have kids?
我们没聊过天 你有孩子吗？
I'd like a piano lesson, please.
我想上钢琴课
I'm with a student now. If you come back tomorrow, I can squeeze you in.
我现在有学生 明天再来，我帮你安排看看
I kind of want to get started. I could give you $1,000.
我想马上开始 我可以给你一千元
Come on in.
进来
Good morning! Off to see the groundhog?
早安！要去看土拨鼠吗？
You think it will be an early spring?
你想今年会是早春吗？
"Winter slumbering in the open air...
“冬天在户外沉睡”
wears on his smiling face...
“展开笑颜”
a dream of spring."
“春天的梦”
How's she look?
雕得怎么样？
- Great. - Thank you.
-很漂亮 -谢谢
Did you know he could ice sculpt?
你知道他会冰雕吗？
Not bad. You say this is your first lesson?
不错，你说这是你第一次上课？
My father was a piano mover.
我爸当过钢琴搬运工
I thought it was you.
菲尔康纳？我就知道是你
I have missed you so much.
我好想你
I don't know where you're headed, but can you call in sick?
我不知道你要去哪 但你能请病假吗？
I gotta get going.
我得走了
It's good to see you.
见到你真好
Hello, father.
老爹
Let's get you someplace warm.
我们找个暖和的地方
Remember me?
记得我吗？
Excuse me, sir. Are you the one who brought the old man in?
抱歉，先生 是你带那位老先生进来的吗？
How is he?
他怎么样？
He just passed away.
他刚过世了
What did he die of?
死因是什么？
He was just old. It was just his time.
年纪大，时候到了
- I want to see his chart. Excuse me. - Sir!
-我要看他的病历，对不起 -先生！
You can't come in here.
你不能进去
This is a restricted area.
这是管制区
Where's the chart?
病历呢？
Sometimes people just die.
人总会死的
Not today.
今天不行
It's hard down there at the bottom.
碗底的不好舀
- Here you go. - Thank you.
-来了 -谢谢
Come on, Dad! Come on, Pop!
起来啊，老爹
When Chekhov saw the long winter...
当契诃夫看到漫长的冬天
he saw a winter bleak and dark and bereft of hope.
他看刺骨黑暗的冬天 还有希望逝去
Yet we know that winter is just another step in the cycle of life.
然而我们知道冬天只是 生命周期的另一步
But standing here among the people of Punxsutawney...
站在普苏塔尼人之间
and basking in the warmth of their hearths and hearts...
靠他们的壁炉和热情取暖
I couldn't imagine a better fate...
漫长而光亮的冬天
than a long and lustrous winter.
也成了最好的时光
From Punxsutawney, it's Phil Connors.
我是菲尔康纳，在普苏塔尼报导
So long.
再会
Very nice speech, Phil.
说得非常好，菲尔
- Thank you. - Thanks.
-谢谢 -谢了
- How was that for you two? - Man, you touched me.
-你们两个觉得怎样？ -我被你感动了
- Thanks, Larry. - Thank you.
-谢了，赖瑞 -谢谢
I gotta go.
我得走了
That was surprising. I didn't know you were so versatile.
真令人惊喜 没想到你这么有才华
I surprise myself sometimes.
有时我自己也很惊讶
Would you like to get some coffee?
想喝点咖啡吗？
I'd love to. Can I have a rain check? I've got some errands to run.
我很想，改天好吗？ 我有事要做
Hold it, fella!
抓好，小子
What do you say?
你该说什么？
You little brat. You have never thanked me!
兔崽子，你从没谢过我
I'll see you tomorrow, maybe!
也许明天见吧
- Now what? - You've totaled it.
-怎么了 -全被你毁了
It's only a flat tire. Now just be patient. Just cool it!
只是爆胎而已，别紧张
- It's an earthquake! - It's not an earthquake!
-是地震！ -不是地震！
What is it?
怎么回事？
Thank you, young man.
谢谢你，年轻人
It's nothing. I had the tire and the jack.
没什么，我有轮胎和千斤顶
Just be comfortable. Be a minute.
坐好，马上好
Who is that?
他是谁？
Must be from the motor club.
一定是修车厂的
- My God! He's having a heart attack! - What should I do?
-天啊，他心脏病发作了！ -怎么办？
- Call an ambulance, a lawyer, a doctor! - Mom, I don't think he's breathing!
-叫救护车、律师、医生！ -妈，他没有呼吸了
I think that did it.
没事了
If you're gonna eat steak, get some sharper teeth.
想吃牛排 就得装锐利一点的牙
- Enjoy your lunch. - Thank you.
-请慢用 -谢谢
Who was that? I'm fine.
他是谁？我没事了
- Are you sure? - Oh, yes. Eat.
-真的吗？ -对，吃吧
People just don't understand what is involved in this.
人们不懂其中奥妙
This is an art form.
这是一种艺术形式
You know, I think most people just think that...
大部分的人会以为
I hold the camera and point it at stuff.
我拿摄影机对着东西拍
There is a lot more to it than just that.
其实不光是那样
Would you be at all interested in seeing the inside of the van?
有兴趣看车上的东西吗？
You know, I really have to get back to the party.
我真的要回派对去了
Great idea. I'll go with you. Let me just drop a tip here.
好主意，我跟你去 我留一点小费
We were just going to the party.
我们要去参加派对
- You going? - Sounds like fun.
-你要去吗？ -好像很好玩
Maybe we should call Phil.
我们应该通知菲尔
- Isn't he good? - He's great!
-他很棒吧？ -棒呆了！
He's my student.
他是我的学生
I'm so proud.
我好骄傲
Thank you.
谢谢
Welcome to our party.
欢迎光临我们的派对
- I didn't know you could play like that. - I'm versatile.
-我不知道你弹得那么好 -我多才多艺
It's that nice, young man from the motor club.
修车厂的年轻人，你真好心
- Thank you again. - It's nothing, ladies.
-再次谢谢你 -没什么，女士
He's the fastest jack in Jefferson County.
他是杰佛逊郡 动作最快的修车工
What was that all about?
那是怎么回事？
I really don't know. They've been hitting on me all night.
我真的不知道 她们整晚一直吃我豆腐
There you are.
你在这里
I never thanked you properly for what you did for Buster.
我还没好好谢谢 你救巴斯特
He would have choked for sure.
他本来一定会噎死的
He may have. He was trying to swallow a whole cow.
可能会，他想吞下一整条牛
- I owe you one, buddy. - Hang onto him, dear. He's a real find.
-我欠你一次，老兄 -好好把握，他是难得的好人
- What did you do today? - Same old, same old.
-你今天做了什么事？ -和平常一样
Excuse me.
对不起
Fred, how was the wedding?
佛瑞，婚礼还好吗？
I just wanted to thank you for making Debbie go through with it.
我要谢谢你让黛比想通了
All I did was fan the flame of her passion for you.
我只是激发她对你的热情
You are the best.
你最棒了
Rita, this is Debbie and Fred Kleiser.
丽塔，这是黛比和佛瑞
- Here you go, kids. Congratulations. - What is this?
-拿去，恭喜你们 -这是什么？
No way!
不会吧
Wrestlemania!
疯狂摔角！
How did you know? We're gonna be in Pittsburgh anyway!
你怎么知道？ 反正我们都要去匹兹堡
- Thank you! You're a real pal! - This is the best!
-谢谢，你真够朋友！ -这才是最棒的
- I don't understand. - I guess not.
-我不懂 -我想也是
How does everyone know you? You only come here once a year.
大家怎么都认识你？ 你一年才来一次
You seem like the most popular person in town.
你好像是城里最受欢迎的人
Excuse me. Dr. Connors?
对不起，康纳医生吗？
I want to thank you for fixing Felix's back.
我要谢谢你治好菲力的背
He can even help around the house again.
他又能整理住家周围了
I'm sorry to hear that, Felix.
真遗憾，菲力
"Dr. Connors"?
“康纳医生”？
It's kind of an honorary title.
那是一种荣誉头衔
- What is going on? - I really don't know.
-怎么回事？ -我真的不知道
There is something going on with you.
你一定在搞什么鬼
Would you like the long version or the short one?
你想听完整版还是浓缩版？
Let's start with the short and go from there.
先从浓缩版开始
Okay, folks. Attention.
好，各位注意
Time for the big bachelor auction. You all know the rules.
拍卖单身汉时间到了 你们都知道规则
All the eligible bachelors come down in front...
有资格的单身汉到前面来
and you ladies bid on them!
女士们请出价
You get to do whatever you want with them. No questions asked!
你们可以和他们做任何事 不准问问题
I don't want to know about it, as long as it's legal!
只要合法 我不想知道你们做什么事
Get out your pocketbooks and remember, it's all for charity!
钱包拿出来 请记得这是慈善活动
What are you doing down here? Go on. Get up there.
你在这里干嘛？上台去啊
I got ten bucks that says you're mine!
我有十块钱，你是我的了
- Buster, I got your first victim. - Come up here!
-我找到第一个受害者 -菲尔康纳，上来吧！
All right! What am I bid for this fine specimen?
好，这位优良男士 该出价多少？
Five dollars!
5块钱
The bidding has begun at five dollars.
从5元起跳
- Ten dollars! - Fifteen!
-10元 -15元
- Sixty! - I'm bid sixty. Do I hear more?
-60，还有更高的吗？
Three hundred and thirty-nine dollars and eighty-eight cents!
339元8毛8！
We can't accept any more bids. That's sold...
我们不接受出价了 就卖给…
to the little lady for $339.88!
出339元8毛8的女士
Congratulations.
恭喜
Okay, bachelors! Who's next?
单身汉们，下一个是谁？
All right! What am I bid for this guy?
好，各位出价多少？
Do I hear a buck and a half?
有人出1块半吗？
Anybody?
有没有？
- Seventy-five cents? - I bid two bits!
-7毛5？ -我出2毛5
Sold to the lady for twenty-five cents!
出2毛5的女士得标
I got him!
我得标了
Phil Connors! I thought that was you!
菲尔康纳，我就知道是你
This is Ned Ryerson, my new insurance agent.
这是尼德莱尔森 我新的保险经纪人
I'll say!
是啊
I have not seen this guy for 20 years.
我有20年没见到这家伙了
He comes to me and buys whole life, term, uniflex...
他跟我买了所有的保险 终身险、单一险
fire, theft, auto, dental, health...
火险、窃盗险、汽车险 牙齿险、健康险
with the optional death and dismemberment plan, water damage.
加上意外死亡、解雇险和水灾险
This is the best day of my life.
今天是我这辈子最棒的一天
Mine too.
我也是
- Where are we going? - Let's not spoil it.
-我们要去哪？ -别搞砸了
I got that!
我懂了
- Why can't I look? - Because you bother me a lot.
-我为什么不能看？ -因为你会让我分心
I'm getting cold. How much longer do I have to sit here?
我很冷，还要坐多久？
I'm just giving you your money's worth. You paid top dollar for me.
我要让你值回票价 你出最高价得标
I think you were a bargain.
我认为你是物超所值
Sweet of you to say. You're probably right.
你这么说真好 也许你说对了
- Is it finished yet? - Almost.
-完成了没？ -快好了
I still have to put cherry syrup on top and then we can eat it.
我还要淋上樱桃糖浆才能吃
Come on! I'm freezing!
快点！我快冻死了！
One second. All right. Let me turn toward the light.
等一下，好了 我把它转向灯光
It's amazing.
不可思议
It's beautiful.
好漂亮
- How did you do that? - I know your face so well...
-你怎么做到的？ -你的脸我非常熟悉
I could have done it with my eyes closed.
我能闭着眼睛做
It's lovely. I don't know what to say.
好漂亮，我不知道该说什么
I do.
我知道
No matter what happens tomorrow...
无论明天发生什么事
or for the rest of my life...
或者往后的生命中发生什么事
I'm happy now because I love you.
我现在都很快乐 因为我爱你
I think I'm happy too.
我也很快乐
- Please, not again. - That is a great song!
-拜，别又来了 -那首歌很棒！
- It's not! - Don't listen to this man...
-才怪 -别听这家伙的…
It's too early.
太早了
Something is different.
有点不一样
Good or bad?
好事还是坏事？
Anything different is good...
只要不一样就是好事
but this could be real good.
不过这真的很好
Why are you here?
你怎么在这里？
I bought you. I own you.
我买了你，你是我的
But why are you still here?
你怎么还在这里？
You said stay, so I stayed.
你叫我留下，我就留下来
I said stay, so you stayed?
我叫你留下你就留下？
I can't even make a collie stay.
连牧羊犬都不听我的话
I gotta check something.
我去看样东西
Stay.
留下来
They're gone!
他们不见了
They're all gone!
他们全都不见了
- Do you know what today is? - What?
-知道今天是什么吗？ -什么？
Today is tomorrow.
今天就是明天
It happened.
发生了
- You're here. - I'm here.
-你在这里 -我在这里
Why weren't you like this last night? You just fell sleep.
你昨晚怎么不像这样子？ 你睡着了
It was the end of a very long day.
昨晚是漫长一天的结束
Is there anything I can do for you today?
今天我能帮你做什么事吗？
I'm sure I can think of something.
我一定会想出事情给你做
It's so beautiful!
好漂亮
Let's live here.
我们住在这里吧
We'll rent to start.
先租一间房子再说